A Finding Aid to the Jacques Lipchitz papers and Bruce Bassett papers concerning Jacques Lipchitz, 1910-2001, bulk 1941-2001, in the Archives of American Art AAA.lipcjacq2
Archives of American Art
- Jacques Lipchitz papers, bulk 1941-1999; circa 1910-1999; Series 1; 9.5 Linear feet Boxes 1-10, OV 11-12; Bassett, Bruce W.; Lipchitz, Jacques, 1891-1973
  - Photographs, circa 1910s-1967; 1.10; 1.7 Linear feet Boxes 8-10
    - People, circa 1910s-1967; 1.10.1
      - With Others (Box 8)
        - With Unidentified Individuals (Photographers: Bernard M. Cohn, Varian Fry, George Moffett, Carl E. Vermilya, and unidentified), 1950-1964 (Box 8, Folder 27)
        - In Studio, Hastings-on-Hudson, NY, with Jane Blaffer Owen and Unidentified Individuals (Photographers: George Holton, Sacha Parma, Whitestone Photo, and unidentified), circa 1960s (Box 8, Folder 28)
      - Lipchitz Family (Box 8)
        - Parents, Abraham and Rachel Krinsky Lipchitz (copy prints), circa 1950s (Box 8, Folder 29)
        - Other Relatives, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 30)
      - Others (Box 8)
        - Josef Albers and Ken Tyler, circa 1964-1965 (Box 8, Folder 31)
        - [Isidore Grossman], Studio Assistant at Work (Photographers: Sacha Parma, and unidentified), circa 1950s (Box 8, Folder 32)
        - Fiore de Henriquez, 1960s (Box 8, Folder 33)
        - Lyndon Baines Johnson, circa 1963-1964 (Box 8, Folder 34)
        - Robert A. Taft, 1950-1953 (Box 8, Folder 35)
          Oversized material housed in Box 10, F3
        - Unidentified Individuals, 1954-1958 (Box 8, Folder 36)
        - Unidentified Groups (Photographers: Luis Guillermo Navarrete and unidentified), circa 1950s (Box 8, Folder 37)
      - Oversized Photographs - Jacques Lipchitz, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 10, Folder 2)
        Oversized material scanned with Box 8, F17 and F21
        Jacques Lipchitz, Hands of
        Jacques Lipchitz in Studio, Hastings-on-Hudson, NY (photographers: Roloff Beny, F. Roy Kemp, George Moffett, Bert Van Bork and unidentified)
      - Oversized Photographs - Others, circa 1950s (Box 10, Folder 3)
        Oversized material scanned with Box 8, F35-F36
        Robert A. Taft
        Unidentified
    - Artwork, circa 1910s-1962; 1.10.2
      The vast majority of this subseries documents Lipchitz's sculpture. Many are unidentified. Among the identified works are: The Joy of Living, Woman and Gazelles, Song of the Vowels (various locations), Prometheus (versions for the Philadelphia Museum of Art and the Ministry of Education, Brazil), Nôtre Dame de Liesse, Assy, France, and ornamental gates and a second cast of Nôtre Dame de Liesse for Philip Johnson's Roofless Church in New Harmony, Indiana. Photographs by Ladislas Segy include "Aspects of Lipchitz Bather III, 1917 bronze on the turntable," which consists of small photographs taken from 11 angles and glued inside a manila folder to document the rotating sculpture. Among the sculpture photographed by F. Wilbur Seiders is a detail of Lipchitz's signature.
      Other works of art by Lipchitz represented in this subseries include a substantial number of photographs of drawings, including pages from sketchbooks which are not among the Jacques Lipchitz papers. Also found is a photograph of a medal bearing a portrait of President Lyndon Baines Johnson commissioned for the Presidential Scholar Awards in 1964.
      Photographs of artwork by other artists include silver objects from the Jewish Museum shown in the Metropolitan Museum of Art's 1955 exhibition "Art of the Hebrew Tradition." The Lipchitz Collection is also represented by 13 examples of African sculpture. "Primitive and Ancient Art" photographs include identified and unidentified items from museums and unspecified collection; it is not known if any are from Lipchitz's collection.
      A substantial number of photographs of sculpture are among the records documenting The Sculpture of Jacques Lipchitz: A Catalogue Raisonné (Subseries 1.5); these have not been scanned. Photographs of artwork by Lipchitz and others, enclosed with letters, are scattered throughout the correspondence (Subseries 1.2) and were scanned with their respective letters.
      Photographs of artwork by Lipchitz are arranged by medium, as are those by other artists. This subseries has not been scanned.
      - By Lipchitz (Box 8)
        - Drawings, circa 1920s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 38-39)
        - Etching, circa 1920s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 40)
        - Medal, circa 1920s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 41)
        - Paintings, circa 1920s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 42)
        - Sculpture, Identified and Unidentified (Box 8)
          - Colton Photos (28A-5558), circa 1950s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 43)
          - James Moore, photographer, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 44)
          - André Morain, photographer, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 45)
          - Ladislas Segy, photographer, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 46)
          - F. Wilbur Seiders, photographer, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 47)
          - Adolph Studley, photographer (AA61-F56), circa 1950s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 48)
          - Adolph Studley, photographer (JL13-JL291), circa 1950s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 49)
          - Adolph Studley, photographer (JL306-JL398), circa 1950s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 50)
          - Adolph Studley, photographer ([JL]400-[JL]494), circa 1950s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 51)
          - Adolph Studley, photographer (JL511-JL857), circa 1950s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 52)
          - Adolph Studley, photographer (K43--Z51, and unnumbered), circa 1950s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 53)
          - [Adolph Studley, photographer](N89-Q46 and unnumbered), circa 1950s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 54)
          - Marc Vaux, photographer (12-698, and unnumbered), circa 1950s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 55)
      - Sculpture, Identified (unidentified photographers), circa 1920s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Sculpture, Unidentified (unidentified photographers) (Box 9)
        - [early 20th century], circa 1920s-1930s (Box 9, Folder 2)
        - #1-34, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 3)
        - #1-104, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 4)
        - Unnumbered, circa 1950s-1970s; 2 Folders (Box 9, Folder 5-6)
      - Sculpture in Interior Settings, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - Sculpture in Outdoor Settings, 1953-1962 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - Sculpture in Outdoor Settings, 1961-1962 (Box 9, Folder 9)
      - Sculpture in Outdoor Settings, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 10)
        Oversized material housed in Box 10, F4
      - By Other Artists (Box 9)
        - Drawings, Unidentified, circa 1970s (Box 9, Folder 11)
        - Mosaic by Hilda Carmel, circa 1970s (Box 9, Folder 12)
        - Paintings, Identified, circa 1970s (Box 9, Folder 13)
          Géricault
          Goya
          Manet
          Nicolas
          Van Gogh
        - Paintings, Unidentified, circa 1950s-1970s; 2 Folders (Box 9, Folder 14-15)
        - Sculpture by Dorothea S. Greenbaum, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 16)
        - Sculpture, Unidentified, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 17)
        - Silver Objects, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 18)
        - Lipchitz Collection, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 19)
        - Primitive and Ancient Art, circa 1950s-1970s; 4 Folders (Box 9, Folder 20-23)
      - Oversized Photographs - Sculpture in Outdoor Settings, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 10, Folder 4)
        Oversized material from Box 9, F10
    - Project Sites and Models, circa 1950s-1970s; 1.10.3
      A few other photographs of project sites, enclosed with letters, can be found scattered throughout the correspondence (Subseries 1.1.2).
      Photographs are arranged alphabetically by name of the institution commissioning the piece, followed by unidentified locations. This subseries has been scanned in its entirety.
      - Hebrew University of Jerusalem (David Harris, photographer), circa 1950s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 24)
      - New Harmony, Indiana (Louis Checkman, photographer), circa 1950s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 25)
      - University of Minnesota, Duluth (unidentified photographer), circa 1950s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 26)
      - Unidentified Location (Lipchitz and others at same site; Cortlandt V. D. Hubbard, photographer), circa 1950s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 27)
      - Unidentified Locations (George Cserna and unidentified photographers), circa 1950s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - Exhibition Installations, 1950-1961; 1.10.4
      Photographs of exhibition installations, enclosed with letters, are also found scattered among the correspondence (Subseries 1.2).
      Exhibition installation photographs are arranged alphabetically by name of the gallery, museum, or institution sponsoring the exhibition, followed by unidentified locations. This subseries has been scanned in its entirety.
      - Battersea Park (London), "London County Council's Invitational Open Air Exhibition of Sculpture" (Mann Brothers, photographer), 1951 (Box 9, Folder 29)
      - Buchholz Gallery (New York), Unidentified Exhibition, circa 1942-1951 (Box 9, Folder 30)
      - The Cincinnati Art Museum, "Jacques Lipchitz, His Sculpture and Drawings, 1914-50" (Edward H. Dwight, photographer), 1951 (Box 9, Folder 31)
      - First Plymouth Church [Plymouth, KS], Exhibition in conjunction with Symposium on Arts and Religion, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 32)
      - Galerie Claude Bernard (Paris), Unidentified Exhibitions (Photograpers: Robert Davis, Yves Hervochon, Luc Joubert, and Jean Michalon), 1956-1961 (Box 9, Folder 33)
      - Gemeentemusea van Amsterdam, Unidentified Exhibition, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 34)
      - Gemeentemuseum Arnhem (Holland), "Sculpture en plein air,", circa 1950s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 35)
      - Har Zion Temple (Philadelphia), "First Annual Art Exhibition on Jewish and Biblical Themes" (Freedman Photos), 1960 (Box 9, Folder 36)
      - Musée d'Art Moderne (Paris), "Jacques Lipchitz,", 1959 (Box 9, Folder 37)
      - The Museum of Modern Art (New York), "The Sculpture of Jacques Lipchitz,", 1954 (Box 9, Folder 38)
      - Portland Art Museum (OR), "Lipchitz: Works 1914-1950" (Edward R. Martin, photographer) (Box 9, Folder 39)
      - Rijksmuseum Kröller-Müller (Otterlo, Holland), "Jacques Lipchitz,", 1958 (Box 9, Folder 40)
      - San Francisco Museum of Art, "Sculpture by Jacques Lipchitz,", 1951 (Box 9, Folder 41)
      - Unidentified Exhibition, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 42)
        photographs with 2 diagrams of galleries indicating sculpture placement
      - Unidentified Exhibitions (Photographers: Bulloz, Japp and Maarten, O. E. Nelson, W. Van Suchtelen, and unidentified), circa 1950s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 43)
    - Events, circa 1952-1966; 1.10.5
      Photographs of The American Jewish Tercentenary Dinner feature President Dwight D. Eisenhower, the main speaker of the evening; Lipchitz does not appear in any views. At the award ceremony sponsored by the Philadelphia Museum School of Art, a citation was presented to Jacques Lipchitz "for the distinction brought upon his profession."
      Posed by Lipchitz's ornamental gates are the participants in the dedication ceremony for the Roofless Church in New Harmony, IN: Philip Johnson, architect; Jacques Lipchitz, sculptor; Jane Blaffer Owen whose Robert Lee Blaffer Trust initiated and funded the project; and chaplain to Queen Elizabeth, Right Rev. George F. Macleod of the Church of Scotland.
      The purpose of Lipchitz's talk to anatomy students at Albert Einstein Medical College was to share a new perspective on the subject of a practicing artist. From the early 1950s through the mid-1960s Lipchitz frequently appeared on "What in the World," a television show that featured experts who identified and discussed unusual items from the collection of the University Museum, University of Pennsylvania.
      Photographs are alphabetically arranged by name of event and chronologically within folders. This subseries has been scanned in its entirety.
      - American Jewish Tercentenary Dinner, New York City (Photographers: Alexander Archer, Wide World Photography, and unidentified), 1954 (Box 9, Folder 44)
      - Award Ceremony, Philadelphia Museum School of Art, 1958 (Box 9, Folder 45)
      - Dedication of Monumental Gates, New Harmony, IN (James K. Mellow, photographer), 1962 (Box 9, Folder 46)
      - Installation of Sculpture Commissions, Unidentified Locations, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 47)
      - Lipchitz Speaks to Medical Students, Yeshiva University, Albert Einstein College of Medicine (Guy Gillette, photographer), 1956 (Box 9, Folder 48)
      - Opening of Studio, Hastings-on-Hudson, NY (Varian Fry, photographer), 1953 (Box 9, Folder 49)
      - "What in the World,", 1953-1966 (Box 9, Folder 50)
    - Places, 1956-1964; 1.10.6
      Some of the unidentified landscapes and views of buildings may be travel pictures. Photographs of the Lipchitz studio at Hastings-on-Hudson, NY show many finished pieces, maquettes, and works in progress. They also give a good sense of the space. The contact sheets include Lipchitz and his studio assistant in a few views. Also found are an undated photograph of Picasso's studio in Paris and one of "Atelier Halser."
      Additional photographs of places, including Lipchitz's studio at Pietrasanta, Italy, are found in the photograph album (Subseries 1.10.7), and may be enclosed with letters scattered throughout the correspondence (Subseries 1.1.2).
      Photographs, arranged by subject, are presented in rough chronological order within each folder. This subseries has been scanned in its entirety.
      - "Atelier Halser" (Yves Hervochon, photographer), circa 1950s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 51)
      - Building Exteriors and Interior, Unidentified, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 52)
      - Landscapes, Unidentified, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 53)
      - Lipchitz Studio (Box 9)
        - Hastings-on-Hudson, NY, 1956-1963 (Box 9, Folder 54)
        - Hastings-on-Hudson, NY (Photographers: The New York Times, Sacha Parma, Whitestone Photo, and unidentified), circa 1940s-1960s (Box 9, Folder 55)
          Oversized material housed in Box 10, F5
        - Hastings-on-Hudson, NY (contact sheets; Gerald Hochman, photographer), circa 1960s (Box 9, Folder 56)
      - Picasso Studio, Paris, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 9, Folder 57)
      - Oversized Photographs - Lipchitz Studio, Hastings-on-Hudson, NY, circa 1940s-1960s (Box 10, Folder 5)
        Oversized material scanned with Box 9, F55
    - Photograph Album, 1967; 1.10.7
      All photographs were taken during the summer of 1967 in Pietrasanta, Italy. The first section contains both color and black and white prints; the second part is all black and white.
      Both sections were removed from the same 3-ring binder and retain their original collation. This subseries has been scanned in its entirety.
      - "Jacques Lipchitz, Peace on Earth, Italy, Summer 1967" and "Jacques Lipchitz Studio Shots Summer 1967," (Box 9, Folder 58)
        Both sections were removed from the same 3-ring binder.
    - Negatives, Slides, and Color Transparencies, 1950s-1965; 1.10.8
      Negatives, slides, and color transparencies are of artwork by Lipchitz. All artwork is unidentified except for a transparency of Sketch for Bull and Condor (watercolor and pencil on paper, created 1913). Two 35-mm color slides show Lipchitz judging a Yonkers Art Association exhibition in the 1950s.
      Additional negatives, slides, and color transparencies are among the catalogue raisonné records (Subseries 1.5). Arranged by record type, this subseries has not been scanned.
      - Negatives - Artwork by Lipchitz, circa 1961-1965 (Box 9, Folder 59)
      - Slides (35-mm, color), circa 1950s (Box 9, Folder 60)
        Artwork by Lipchitz
        Lipchitz Judging Yonkers Art Association Exhibition
      - Color Transparencies, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 61)
        Lipchitz with Sculpture
- Bruce Bassett papers concerning Jacques Lipchitz, 1961-2001; Series 2; 43.3 Linear feet Boxes 13-67, OV 68-69
  The Bruce Bassett papers concerning Jacques Lipchitz measure 43.3 linear feet and date from 1961 to 2001. The series consists mainly of materials related to Bassett's extensive audiovisual documentation projects concerning the life and art of the sculptor Jacques Lipchitz. Also found are paper records including letters, business records, printed materials, and paper production records related to the audiovisual projects. Other projects, unrelated to Lipchitz, include video and sound recordings related to Sidney Lifchez, IBM, Isamu Noguchi, the Storm King Sculpture Center, and Auguste Rodin.
  Original sound recordings and photographs from Deborah Stott's 200 hour oral history with Jacques Lipchitz are found, as well as detailed, typewritten summaries of its content. Documentation used in Bassett's film projects about Lipchitz include original film and sound recordings from Bassett's 40 hours of interviews with Lipchitz from 1971, and film documentation of the posthumous installations of Lipchitz's large-scale sculptures in Philadelphia, New York, and Israel in the late 1970s. In addition to the raw footage from these projects, which is incomplete, the collection contains workprint and final, edited works Bassett created in multiple versions and formats, and paper records documenting the film projects' creation, production, and later use.
  Among the papers related to the film projects are scripts, an index to original footage, programming notes, film lab records, exhibition materials, an extensive collection of questions about Lipchitz gathered from the public for the interactive project, and other production records. Other papers include letters from Lipchitz and his wife, business correspondence, financial records, contracts, project files, and printed materials.
  Records of other projects, unrelated to Jacques Lipchitz, are also found, including video and sound recordings from Bassett's projects about the designer Sidney Lifchez, IBM, the Storm King Sculpture Center, Isamu Nogichi, and Auguste Rodin. Other projects not created by Bassett but found among his papers include two news films related to John F. Kennedy during his presidency, a screenplay entitled The Man with Two Sides to His Head by Anthony Cave Brown, the film Man Is My Name, by Pierre Dominique Guisseau, and a portion of the film Dream on Monkey Mountain.
  - Jacques Lipchitz Letters, 1970; 2.1; 2 Folders Box 13
    This series consists of letters written by Jacques Lipchitz, and one letter fragment written by Lipchitz's wife. One folder contains photocopies of eleven letters written by Jacques Lipchitz to unnamed correspondents between 1927 and 1931. Letters are in French and concern sculpture commissions and personal matters. Also found are two letters written by Lipchitz to Bruce Bassett about their work together and a fragment of a letter from Lipchitz's wife to Bassett.
    - Letters (1927 - 1931), undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
      General note
      location of originals is unknown
    - Letters to Bruce Bassett, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Business Records, 1968-2001; 2.2; 1.3 Linear feet Boxes 13-14
    This series contains tax records, correspondence, invoices, contracts, releases, and project files concerning the work Bassett produced under the auspices of the Jacques Lipchitz Art Foundation and Histor Systems, two organizations he founded. Both entities were concerned mainly with projects documenting the life and work of Jacques Lipchitz, and both contain materials related to the two main Lipchitz projects, namely the documentary and the interactive video installation. The Jacques Lipchitz Art Foundation was dissolved in part because of the Lipchitz family's concerns that its existence would confuse and complicate transactions involving Lipchitz artworks after his death.
    The series is arranged as 2 subseries:
    2.2.1: Jacques Lipchitz Art Foundation, 1968-1982
    2.2.2: Histor Systems, 1991-2001
    - Jacques Lipchitz Art Foundation, 1968-1982; 2.2.1
      The Jacques Lipchitz Art Foundation was founded by Bruce Bassett in 1968. Projects carried out through the Foundation include the the audioguide created for the Brooks Memorial Art Gallery, the Deborah Stott Interviews (Subseries 2.4), Jacques Lipchitz Interactive Project (Subseries 2.5.2), Jacques Lipchitz Documentary (Subseries 2.5.3). The Jacques Lipchitz Art Foundation dissolved around 1978, but Bassett carried on with his work related to Jacques Lipchitz under the auspices of Histor Systems (Subseries 2.2.2).
      Subseries includes financial records, organizational records, correspondence, contracts, and project files related to the major projects carried out through the Foundation. The Bylaws folder includes a list of the JLAF Board of Directors from 1971. Notable documents in Correspondence include a letter from Nelson Rockefeller to Lipchitz, and letters about the creation of a Jacques Lipchitz Sculpture Museum (which never came to pass). The Contracts and Releases folder includes the original media release signed by Jacques Lipchitz. The Brooks Memorial Art Gallery project files document the production of an audioguide in conjunction with a 1974 Jacques Lipchitz exhibition at Memphis, TN museum through correspondence, checklists, drafts of a script, and photographs. The documentary project files contain records of fundraising and distribution of the film, a list of music used, and correspondence describing changes to 1977 version of film. The interactive project files consist mainly of documents related to a demonstration of the interactive system in December, 1973.
      Additional documentation of the interactive project is found in series 2.2, Business Records, Histor Systems, and in series 5.2, Film Projects, Interactive Project. A long interview with Lipchitz and a large collection of photographs, both produced under the auspices of the Jacques Lipchitz Art Foundation, are found in series 4, Interview with Jacques Lipchitz conducted by Deborah Stott.
      - Financial Records, 1968-1975 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Bylaws, 1968-1971 (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence, 1968-1971 (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - Deborah Stott Letters, 1968-1977 (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Contracts and Releases, 1971-1978 (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Brooks memorial Art Gallery Project Files, 1973-1974; 6 Folders (Box 13, Folder 8-13)
      - Documentary Project Files, 1974-1980; 4 Folders (Box 13, Folder 14-17)
      - Interactive Project File, 1973-1982 (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - Histor Systems, 1991-2001; 2.2.2
      Bruce Bassett founded Histor Systems to continue his work on the Jacques Lipchitz interactive project, as well as some work connected to the Lipchitz Documentary, after the Jacques Lipchitz Art Foundation was dissolved. Under this organization, Bassett also worked to promote the interactive system for use documenting other notable public figures, without success.
      This series primarily contains records relating to the presentation of the Lipchitz interactive project, which was usually presented under the title "Conversations with Lipchitz." There are also records relating to the Lipchitz documentary and its later releases with French and Spanish subtitles. Other records in the series include invoices mostly addressed to Hanno Mott, records relating to a demonstration of the interactive system in Israel, and an interactive project file that includes informative and promotional letters about Histor Systems, most notably addressed to Bill Gates and President Jimmy Carter (at the time, a prospective subject for an interactive project). The Interactive Project Files includes a list of Histor Systems directors in 1996.